howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is hanzi freinect a
political philosopher historian
and sociologist he's the author of the
listening society
and nordic ideology he spends much of
his time
alone in the swiss alps he operates the
very interesting website
metamoderna and as usual we'll have
pointers to
the website and the books on our episode
page at jimrutshow.com
hunty was on the show in january where
we discussed his book the listening
society
today we're going to mostly focus on his
second book
nordic ideology i actually started
reading nordic ideology first
and i figured hey i'm a reasonably smart
fellow i can interpolate from context
what i need from
the first book the listening society
well it turned out i was wrong by the
time i got to about the 45
mark according to my kindle in nordic i
realized i really need to go back and
read the listening
so i did so that's what i'd suggest if
you find this book really interesting i
suggest
make the effort and read listening
society first then nordic audiology
nonetheless in the spirit of getting
listeners up to speed
i'm going to ask hanzi to go into a
couple of the key concepts
from the first book the listening
society before we jump into nordic
ideology
and the core of the first book is
an idea that hanzi calls the effective
value meme
it's essentially a four-dimensional
space
of thinking about human adult
development
so hanzi why don't you tell the audience
about the effective value i mean
in some level of detail take a few
minutes
well thank you first uh for welcoming
back uh me back to the show
i'd like to say then about effective
value meme that
a lot of people are familiar with
something quite similar
uh namely um value memes from the spiral
dynamics uh thinking
and it's just not just in the spiral
dynamics uh framework it's
all over develo adult development
psychology really that people have
noticed
and it's not just actually in adult
development psychology it's also in
anthropology those anthropologists that
still
or again start believing in the stage
development and the evolution of stages
of societies
they notice that there is a pattern here
they notice that
um people in
smaller societies and and farther back
in history tend to believe
more in magic and then rituals and
rights for instance in
and things go on from there to larger
and larger
core principles or universal stories or
narratives
and perhaps gods or perhaps
one god over all gods which
which unify many people many
perspectives
and so on and find one higher truth the
truth higher than any person
and then people go on from there to
noticing that hey there are many visions
of this
one god there are many visions of
objective reality
so um and and then in modern society
even
that objective reality seems to break
down under the weight of so many
perspectives some people start to wander
into what's called
post-modern uh perspectives and ideas
and so so these things align
anthropology
history psychology and
personality they they align around
some kind of stages which are
recognizable
and even in any society then people
aren't just of one stage that that
correspond to that kind of
society rather you can see on the one
hand that people have
learned a certain code or demeanor or
world view from the society that we have
that we've been brought up in
but at the same time we also develop
differently
as human beings as persons some people
never really grasp the society and the
narratives
we're in or have and go back to
ways of grasping the world that which
would have resonated more with
earlier societies others go on and
pick up more conventional views and some
even
start to experiment with
post-conventional views which may
intuit perhaps societies of the future
or
or future forms of human life and and
life philosophies so an example would be
that
in late medieval times there were some
intuitions
of uh of the renaissance and modernity
for instance roger bacon
this monk was before his time in i
believe that
may have been the late 13th century and
he
uh he intuited that we will
study nature and we and there will be
wagons that roll without without horses
and there will be
machines flying in the air and boats
made of metal
traversing the sea um with no sails and
so on
and he didn't really know about any of
the technology or couldn't guess on it
but he was before his time he was
thinking
already according to uh well according
to what
and there it is a value meme which
corresponded to a society
after his own he was before his time in
that
in that developmental sense
so in any population let's say you're in
switzerland uh you're going to have some
kind of uh
normal distribution that's not exactly a
normal distribution but
but something along those lines with
some people
having simpler world views and and
and effective value means that come
before that would have resonated with
earlier societies
a large bulk of people who resonate with
what's conventionally swiss and uh
2020s for instance and then a
minority of people who already are
hooked on to
some kind of cultural resonance which
perhaps is more of what is going to
emerge
or emerging already and i call these
then
effective value meme because the the
theory here i'm
commenting upon is called spiral
dynamics and it has
these color codes for these different
value
memes so you can have traditional values
you can have modern values you can
post modern values traditional values
would be more authoritarian and you
believe in
maybe one one god one truth one religion
modern values would be perhaps more
achiever oriented
and have to do with business and
democracy and
well a materialist reductionist world
view for instance and post-modern values
would be
well seeing the world more relationally
and having more egalitarian views and
wanting to soften the hard and harsh
sides and destructive sides of modern
life and society so
the the problem i noticed with this
developmental view was that people seem
to fit in some ways within these
categories and in others they didn't so
see
some people were complex thinkers
and but maybe
spiritually relatively relatively flat
some people have profound
emotional and spiritual depths
but they're not necessarily super smart
some people are very learned
in terms of all the progressive ideas
out there
but understand them in flattened ways
and so so they have they're reduced to
cliches
and so on so there appear to be at least
four four dimensions then
that put together is not a necessarily a
value meme that is recognizable as such
but if you put them together
there is still a pattern that is vaguely
recognizable
and that's why i call them effective
valuement meme
in effect this person will reproduce the
values of
modern society why well because they are
at a certain
you mentioned four four dimensions
they are at a certain level of
complexity in terms of their
thinking they have a certain world view
which they have imbued from
our surroundings they have a certain
certain level of introspective
individuation or dividuation as a human
being knowing their own emotions and so
on
and defining their own self and their
own life philosophy
and they may have a certain level of
subjective states or
or happiness which facilitate this kind
of
life and participation and this these
kinds of values i mean if you
feel really bad about yourself all the
time it's just difficult to be a good
achiever democrat for instance
or have the patience to believe in in a
scientific world view
if things get too rocky maybe a magical
worldview
with quick fixes will be more tempting
for instance
so these put together i'm saying that
yes spiral dynamics and yes uh
developmental psychologists and
anthropologists you are on to something
we should just
pick these dimensions apart and put them
back together
and this has certain i mean it makes
a few things a lot easier like the
conventional
spiral dynamics or developmental
psychologists which look at this
one dimensionally they run into problems
whenever they look at people
compare people from two different
societies so let's say you have a
medieval genius
and you have a contemporary
14 year old from i don't know mexico or
whatever average country of the world
today
and um the the medieval genius let's say
it's thomas of aquinas
uh in his adult life and so if you
compare the
14 year old mexican of today well they
were taught physics in school right
so they have a more advanced world view
and they understand
the nature of reality better than
the most complex mind of a generation of
a whole continent
which i mean somehow we know this
doesn't make sense
so we will just say that the kid has
acquired a more advanced code because
they
were brought up in in a larger society
with with more complex code but thomas
of aquinas
is more capable of uh
making um an independent uh
thought pattern or idea and he will
bring more emotional depth to
his search for the truth so so in the
end
maybe you can say that thomas of aquinas
has higher
effective value mean than the 14 year
old
or maybe just different in the
four-dimensional space right
to put your labels on it first dimension
you called hierarchical complexity and
you
had 15 levels which seemed reasonable
enough going all the way back to the
simplest organism
i think level one would have been a
bacteria approximately and then
your second which you called code which
is essentially
culture that was downloaded to you i
love the example that hey the 14 year
old kid in
mexico city knows quite a bit more about
physics than thomas aquinas did but
on average thomas aquinas is going to
have a much higher
hierarchical complexity in his thinking
you know state
being the emotional set point that
you're normally at
is dimension three again as i understood
it and then
the fourth which was to me a little less
clear you called
depth i believe and depth i took to mean
the range of states one had had during
one's life approximately
is that a reasonable way to describe the
four dimensions it is i mean
qualifying the fourth one at depth then
uh the the range
of well so so first of all states aren't
um
are necessarily reducible to emotions
emotions
tend to have a directionality or and
they tend to have a target
thing and they tend to be impetus or
drive for for action or agency they're
in a way the subjective side of the fuel
of of motivation or agency like you
you get angry and then your body
prepares to move something
out of your way violently if you have to
for instance
um and if you can't do that then you
feel really sad about that
and then you go into your body wants to
protect itself for instance
but states are just the the sense of
being alive
uh of just existing
and we've all noticed hopefully by now
that
just being alive feels differently from
time to time and sometimes
feel feeling alive has this
profound sense of directness and
openness and crispness to it and those
are high states
when we're in heaven in some sense which
is not the same as just being happy
we can even be sad in heaven if our
heart opens up and
flows and it's like river and uh
everyone is forgiven and things are
brought back into harmony through this
deep sorrow
for instance so that would be a high
state with uh
with a sad emotion but on the other hand
on the other side of the states there
are like
if you get stuck i don't know in a bad
dream
or you wake up at night and things just
don't make sense and the reality doesn't
seem to fit together and
and there's a profound terror or
darkness or
on a bad psychedelic trip for instance a
lot a lot of people these days have
these experiences
and they can feel stuck in an internal
eternal loop
so it's worse than death that because
you fall out into a space of nothingness
which is just pure terror for instance
those are real
really low states um and what when you
uh then encounter going from the states
to the depth when you encounter
spiritual particular practitioners
you can notice things about them they
will when they say
stuff about their uh purpose in life it
will be
uh something more universal and and
and spiritual and something more
embodied and felt
and when when you look them in the eyes
they will be
a little bit like they have like these
deeper tunnels
of their eyes uh inside them uh
and if you look at their movements they
tend to be a little bit softer at least
when they
when they approach certain states that
have to with their depth
and this comes from from hard
contemplative work
which generally speaking means
integrating those states so those states
can
put those states can put you like put
your whole system
or nervous system in a certain state yes
but could you go from there to remember
that state to make it a part
of who you are as a person to make it
into a trait that's the depth part
that's you remember that oh
life really is a kind of potential
heaven
right life really is a potential hell
and if you
sense those things um
on a very real and visceral level and
you remember them and those are
recurring drives in your life then you
take life both much more seriously on
the dark side
and you take life much more as as a
cosmic joke on the light side
um and and that's kind of depth uh it's
not well it's a half a theory i'll admit
it
but it's there's something there and
what i find is that these deep
people they align spontaneously with the
progressive
uh ideas ideas about complexity ideas
about
uh non-judgmental hierarchical
development
ideas about uh crossing different
paradigms and
and and multicultural perspectives from
from civilizations
ideas of creating a profound a more
profound
existential peace at the heart of what
it means to be human in our
in our society and so on all of these
ideas would which i
or which i feel pertain to
the later stages the the
the kind of civilization that is only
being born now
they seem to correlate with people
having high depth
now the problem is as we discussed last
time the high depth people
if they're not also complex thinkers and
have good code they
tend to fall into magical thinking um
and that's
uh that's another story so all of these
developmental qualities they come with
risks
and they come with downsides so if
you're really really
complex thinker but you're not very deep
you tend to
be crude or reductionist but if you're
really really deep but you're not so
complex you fall into
i don't know eckhart hall is stuff um
and a cartel is
he has high stakes he has great depth
but if you
open his books and read his theories
about humanity and reality or
or listen to his commentary on what's
going on in the world it's it's gobbly
gook
yep we see that a lot unfortunately
thank you for that good review and
particularly for
elucidating depth well help me
understand it a little bit better
i must say since i read the book and
also particularly since we had our
conversation i have actually been
using this four-dimensional model and
trying to think about the world and
sharing some of the ideas with some of
my friends particularly in the game b
space and
actually in game b land people are now
using this language to a greater or
lesser degree
and while as you say is it actually a a
solid theory yet
no but is it a useful rule of thumb or
heuristic i'd say yes
and i have a thought or two i like to
run back by you and see what you think
in the thinking and conversations i've
had one of the thoughts is that state is
relatively easy to modify
give someone some lsd and you'll change
their state right
but the effect may not be very clear
about what that change is and may not
last long a lot of the research done on
psychedelics
is that the biggest effect is about six
months
on the other hand for some people the
trip is sufficiently strong it also
impacts their depth and then they will
say that it had a
you know a lifetime's worth of
experience but
it's you know kind of a random weapon in
some sense hard to say
what the effect will be and how long
it'll last hierarchical complexity is
probably the most powerful single
dimension of your model
but two things one it has i think all
the evidence shows so far
significant innate component right
mental horsepower
is you know somewhere between 50 and 80
heritable or at least the capability to
develop
that of course it's very important to
realize that the achieved
cognitive complexity is a mixture of
both innate
and environment if you have gene set x
but you're
raised in a cave by a wolf you're not
going to develop a high level of
hierarchical complexity
and then here's the other one from terms
of the levers on society
really it takes a lifetime of effort to
move it up
and it's a slow hard process
so that had brought me to think this is
what i'd love to get your reaction to
that code is probably the most salient
lever point
because code affects the others right if
you have the right code you have a
culture that engenders hierarchical
complexity to the level people have the
capability
if you have the right code that means
institutions
ways of treating each other that lead to
greater state
greater state in some cases will lead to
greater depth
so i'm thinking that for those of us who
are interested in
what comes next and building a better
world putting a lot of our effort in
code is useful in fact in our game b
world
some of our foundational documents were
written by a guy named jordan hall
collaborator of mine and he has put them
in a collection called deep code
that you can find on medium just type in
jordan hall deep code
and you'll get there i guess one final
thought before i get your reaction
when i tried to really think abstractly
about what the nordic ideology book
is one could say it's a code book
essentially but a code book that
provides
routines in the code to affect the other
three states so with that i'll let you
react
well so so first of all uh bingo uh
i i very much agree um and um
and i mean there are a bunch of things
uh to to
to say about this but yes that's why i'm
a writer
i mean uh when i was younger i was very
interested in meditation
still am but i i think like
well whatever i can do or achieve uh
as a singular human being in that
regard is just not scalable and
transferable
uh to the same degree so that's i mean
for this reason i didn't pursue um
a life of more pure spirituality you can
practice uh complex thought uh and
it can be leveraged so so so when when
you look at mhc
uh people keep coming back to me about
this and i i
i appreciate that you that you bring the
realist perspective here which is
my perspective also people are
tenacious about this that they really
really want us to
uh to they really want mhc to be
uh movable and learnable the cognitive
complexity the
stage of cognitive complexity of a
person and they want to shake up their
friends and
or or climb or we ourselves climb
in in cognitive complexity and sure
enough
these things do happen i mean the 15
stages but depending on how you count
you could count up to 17 stages even
and everybody passes through these
stages and and everybody
passes at least to stage i mean a normal
adult will pay a pass to stage 9
10 11 or 12. so that's
that's i mean that's plenty
so uh so this happened 12 times already
in somebody's life since you're a
fetus um so which is quite interesting
right
so so in one way it's apparently
the most movable one but once you have
an adult human being here and now and
you sit down with them
what are you going to do like to change
the complexity of somebody's thinking
this is how radical it is you will have
to
i mean the the demand would be you'd
have to get them to
start inventing patterns of thoughts
according to more complex patterns
which their brain has thus far never
formed
in their life so i mean you don't just
do that
over over over the dinner table right
you can affect
perhaps the whole environment over a
long time
with exposure and with practice and with
scaffolding meaning uh help from other
people and
repetition then perhaps these things can
be shifted
and these things align with stuff they
they find in the brain
if you study the the uh the abstract
algebra of people's
patterns in their brains you can see
that they actually
that thoughts go up to 11 dimensions
and this may actually mirror
a lot of what it means to uh to have
patterns of different stages of
complexity that
more parts of your brain work together
and then you kind of see something more
abstract than you can that you can name
and our language often stops working
after a while
but all the sciences do point in the
direction of higher complexity
so you can climb this but it's hard
it's really really hard to do something
with an actual person
what is very actionable like you said
again i can't say better myself is the
code system
meaning that given that there is a large
subpopulation of high complexity
high state relatively high state and uh
and a higher depth than usual than
the norm then these people can be armed
with or
equipped or cultivate a
higher stage of complexity in terms of
their code
meaning that the the base suppositions
about reality about society
about uh where we're going about our own
place in it about how we define
ourselves about how we define
relationships
all of these things can change
relatively easily all you need to do is
to get
and grok some new ideas and then you can
start using them
that being said um those ideas
are only really usable to that
subportion of the population which have
the corresponding complexity so we're
left with a challenge to develop all of
these dimensions
because just ideas just code with
with it no brains to run them
no hearts to fill it and so on is of
course meaningless
so that's that's one one reaction the
other reaction
that i have is the metamodernist
wars the culture wars or the
metamodernist version of culture wars
which we have
and people will will have noticed one of
these
four dimensions as fundamental to life
so some people will have noticed state
they'll say
whoa if people could only
understand the power of zen vipassana
and some other profound practice or
or a psychedelic perhaps experience and
so on uh
and and maybe a training program and and
uh some
some health stuff things that help your
sleep and they then they notice how
awake you feel how alive you feel
and they say okay here's here's the
answer on all the rest is
other people will go to all of these
group dynamic
workshops and then they'll work on their
traumas and masculinities and they'll
get in touch with their deepest emotions
and they'll
be brave and cry about childhood
stuff that happened to them and get
their insecurities out in the open and
own that stuff and then they'll feel
stronger more integrated and they will
see whoa
this is and all the
like you can pour how many words or
intellectual ideas but this is how you
really change a person and then
they're also right and some people will
notice
hey people are looking at the world flat
and i see
spheres and they're seeing circles and
we should get people to be more complex
we should get people to think in more
multi-dimensional ways and we should get
people to grok
more abstract realities so that people
can together
resonate on more wicked and abstract
topics
which require us to grasp topologies and
and fractals and all the rest of it
which our brains are actually capable of
and those will emphasize growth
and cognitive complexity and then there
is the code people
who will have one or two or three or
five favorite ideas and philosophies and
then maybe
they will be in love with process
philosophy maybe they will be in love
with complexity theory or something else
right
and they say if people only understood
this so what we have here is
like i believe we should see this
multi-dimensionality
and we should see that code is in fact
the greatest leverage point but of
course
in the in the long run all four are are
equal and the people who
people should stop fighting about this
stuff and and
see that we got different parts of the
elephant
and then think about code as a way to
help up regulate the other three
and of course vice versa so yeah all
right let's move on a little bit let's
get into the book itself a little bit
one of the things i 100 agree with this
is a battle i've been fighting since i
was 20
since i was 11 actually and had a
epiphany about
reality you say it is what we haven't
woken up to however
is the fact that we can change the
societal barriers and social
psychological landscapes
of everyday life you know i i pound the
table all the time says all this stuff
that we don't like we can
change it right turns out one of the
areas i've done a lot of work on
is monetary theory and alternative
monetary systems
and it drives me crazy that people have
reified the concept of money
and they confuse money with wealth for
instance right and they think that
fractional reserve banking mediated by
central bankers was somehow brought down
from mount sinai
by moses and yet the reality is it's a
series of frozen
accidents and conscious design decisions
that have given us a
specific set of social institutions
norms and beliefs
but all those things can be changed i
took that as
the deepest theme of your book actually
the particular section which you which
you name uh
it has to do with the with this shift
from from
seeing that we can change the natural
world to seeing that we can change
the the social world and in a way it
sounds
it sounds obvious but it but it really
isn't um
that before the natural sciences
made this great entrance into reality
into our our shared view of reality
we had no idea i mentioned roger bacon
earlier
that some few people could see like okay
if you really understand the nature of
reality
the physical nature of things you can
make things do
stuff that you couldn't imagine you can
make
cars run without horses and so on today
then we
we run into these barriers of of of the
natural world
the environmental barriers and then the
climate change and all the rest
of it and then we're together waking up
to
okay we have environmental systemic
barriers that are going to stop us
from thriving and continuing
at the same time there's no reason to
believe those barriers are
only environmental there are just as
much cognitive mental
uh well they have to do with with the
deep code of society and
and the culture we live in so the shift
and if modern society was the society
which could
see nature and then according to its
cultural code
change nature until poof this happens
and here i am in a house where
everything is produced from
places around the world and it's plastic
and it's concrete and it's wood
and and silicon for that matter and all
of these things
put together according to some some
principle
that that run our societies well
the next step would be to see those
principles of our societies
and make them visible and start taking
them as an
object of change as an object of
awareness so that would be
a core definition of a meta-modern
society a society that goes beyond
and looks through modern society
and in which the the if
modern society before used to be a box
taken for
for granted now we can look inside the
box we can see all of his constituent
elements we can see
uh how its norms are formed how how
people's selves develop sense of self
develop how
psychology is develop how interactions
are shaped through
everything from architecture to uh to
interior design to institutions to
language and so on
and we start reworking nature so this
becomes kind of like
one of those strange loop things yep
we're changing the code that modifies
our self which we use to modify our code
right
yeah and i mean and it's high time we do
it i mean uh so so douglas hofstadter
wrote this i am a strange loop and
society in this sense
must become a strange loop that we we
have to be able to see
the code that we ourselves are going to
run on
so yes i am a robot no i have no free
will or maybe i do in some philosophical
deep last instance but i am going to
follow the structures of language and
grammar given to handed to me by
all the rest of you all i'm just going
to do so
i and if i try to do something else then
even then i will be structured uh
by by my environment so let's let's
grasp that deep environment and and
restructure it
and that's a humongous task i mean
it's it's tremendous in its immensity
how how do we even start doing so and
just to say something about how
important it is that we start evolving
in that direction now
and this speaks to another another
contemporary author uh max
tegmark this uh this futurist and and
physicist
he writes in in life 3.0 that
okay now we're reaching the point where
we're actually going to design
intelligent computers uh it's one part
ai you're
you're into that a lot um but also we
can redesign biological life
so these things taken together we're
going to
right now we are going to re-make
biology itself
according to our cultural code so that
the potential for creating suffering
is immense so unless the cultural code
itself
becomes self-aware and starts operating
and upon itself in a feedback cycle
improving upon itself
not least to to you know get more
complex ethics to
to update its the coded runs on to to
have
greater depth in its compassion to
operate from
higher states of playfulness and so on
then we can create suffering
as it has never been seen before so
these are very very very serious matters
um at this particular historical or i
suppose you could even say
trans-historical time because we're kind
of jumping off
one one axis of historical development
and
and uh going in a completely other
direction
that it's we're entering some kind of
post-human
history which is isn't necessarily
continuous
with uh with the history of humanity as
we have conventionally thought about it
yep and i would add another endorsement
for life 3.0 a truly
mind-expanding book by max tegmark well
worth reading
let me propose sort of the classic
argument
against you know this idea that we have
to intelligently
develop our social operating system
the classic kickback and i hear it all
the time when i talk about these things
and
when we talk about game b is oh isn't
that social engineering
and you know what kind of hubris is that
to think that we should
consciously engineer our society i
should also add those
people who i disagree with i'm not
endorsing this view but i hear it all
the time
and didn't social engineering the idea
that we can do better
lead us to nightmares like nazism and
marxist leninism
right so first of all it's
it's correct uh social engineering is
dangerous
but that something is dangerous distance
that it's uh
powerful and then you have to do it
right uh so
if if social engineering brought us
marxism and leninism it also brought us
the us constitution
and and the basis of democracy and the
tripartite division of powers
people came up with this stuff uh
montesco came up with it uh
quite specifically and and some people
work then to
uh institute these things as as
technologies as uh as engineer devices
so
there is always and has always been an
interplay between
the chance and what we cannot control
and the stuff we
we can control and canon should try to
uh
and then the the the right balance is
difficult to know but you have to then
explore what the right balance is
the the neoliberal idea uh would be that
the markets is spontaneously organized
and then the state
is well basically control freak
mechanism by which human beings steer
and and and control and and suffocate
human creativity and and so on
but it doesn't actually make sense why
would agency
when controlled through the state be
inherently
oppressive and why would markets then be
inherent
and on all the human agency that happens
through them be inherently
self-organizational obviously both
things can be both oppressive
and self-organizational and no states
exist without
corresponding markets and no markets
actually exist without corresponding
states
the same goes for the third dimension a
civil society
such as you and me having this
discussion without it actually being
either a market or a state-defined
relationship in any way so um
i mean these these three things develop
together
um and the the idea is so and there is
no real
clear really clear um
distinction between what is engineering
and what is just participation
and having an opinion and wanting to do
something
so the the reductio ad absurdum
i mean if you if you take it to its
extreme the position i am against social
engineering it also means you can't
clean your kitchen
because hey who are you to say that
the dustbin should be underneath the
sink and if you try to control it then
bad things are going to come out of it
well
obviously then if you're never going to
control everything anything you
yeah you can't you literally can't get
out of bed
uh so so it's it it's not bad to have
a natural want for power in the sense
uh power as creativity as
participation as a freedom and my
freedom doesn't really
stop at my outer border and begin at
your outer border it's actually i become
more free if you scaffold me by playing
interesting
things back to me right uh or by by
resonating with me and so
on it's it's actually a zero
it's it's not a real question uh the
thing about social engineering or not
uh it's a real concern and the concern
would be
if we can specify what i think people
really mean
do you think that you as an elite
should force your opinion on others if
you know it better through the monopoly
of violence of the state for instance
and then the answer is going to be no
most of the time
and sometimes yes in extreme cases for
instance on
let's say criminality it makes sense for
us to you to have monopolies of violence
but in most cases we should go as
liberal and lenient
as possible yes it makes sense to put
breivik the terrorists who shot a shot
up 100 people
in jail against his will it makes sense
and that we should do it by police force
um
but uh well and then if we want to
really really kill the anti social
engineering
argument the the last and final
one is well okay we currently have
schooling and schooling includes
basically brainwashing people into a
certain language and worldview for 12
years
and if you are against any kind of
discussion about that in the name of
being against engineering then you're
actually
closing down one of the most important
democratic discussions that we could
possibly have
so you're closing down freedom you're
not opening up for it
it's rather by saying that oh we are
being brainwashed by this society
that we are in either way why don't we
make that
into democratically owned
self-organizing process which is
made as conscious as possible and not
steered by unconscious
processes and manipulations and power
relations that's
that's the answer really and i would
agree and i would add one
caveat which is i think it's really
important
for those of us who are engaging in
something like social engineering
to understand the epistemological limits
of complex systems the whole idea of
emergence which
i think you and i would both agree in
fact you use the term in your book
we're looking to cultivate better
emergences in complex system called
society
and one of the things paradoxically we
know about emergencies is they're
essentially impossible to predict from
previous state
though that might be a little overstated
and so i'd suggest that
one should think about the warning about
social engineering to mean
thinking that you can predict more than
you really can about the unfolding of a
complex system
and be sure that you're always thinking
about interventions to steer the system
towards what we think to be a better
place
as a series of probes and tests that
have to be
empirically verified and with an
experimental mindset
and then the other one which i'm trying
to introduce into game b for whatever
reason some people don't like the term
is rather than to compel people to move
to a new system
we should seduce them to move to a new
system
the idea struck me when i was thinking
about the collapse of marxist leninism
in
eastern europe you know the reason they
all wanted to get the hell out to say
the east germans
and the poles and the hungarians was
they were seduced by the fact that they
were receiving tv and radio broadcasts
from the west and they saw
gosh you know our country is gray and
grim and full of spies
and very few fun and interesting things
these other people seem like they're
having a whole lot more fun
so literally the germans and the poles
and the hungarians were seduced
to adopt the liberal democratic
market-driven
state away from marxist leninism and if
we
have the epistemological modesty of
complex systems
and the idea that people should be
seduced rather than compelled we can
avoid some of the dangers of social
engineering
yes uh i agreed and whenever uh
compelling by force is necessary then we
can be pretty sure we're working against
the attractor points yes a good example
would be the cool locks in
in the soviet union so they thought ah
the future of society is probably
collective uh
collective big collective farms uh which
are
been uh owned by i don't know abstract
level by the state and so on
and then why do these uh
middle class farmers don't want this
uh we have to force them and then they
end up killing a lot of kulaks and and
sending them to
gulag and so on and of course if you
have to do that then
probably the behavioral forces
are not working in your directions and
you should try to work with the
behavioral forces right
whereas if you look at
some kind of future post-capitalist
system
would have to out-compete capitalism on
its own terms
yep and i love that fact from your book
and again it's very much game b
that if we're really doing this right we
should be able to
out-compete and then seduce people away
from the status quo if that's what we
want to do
another major theme at least what i took
to be a major theme
maybe the second biggest major theme of
your book
this is a quote from the book the
emotional well-being of people
is just as important as their economic
welfare
this would be a society where depression
stress and alienation
have become political issues in the same
vein as security
jobs and housing are today
yes uh so uh that's an important theme
that it's not
that we can just make one topic
in politics and we would cover all of
those issues
because they're not i mean the more
complex and the more
intimate issues we we grapple with and
i guess we'll get there later in the
interview when we talk about these
six dimensions of uh
politics i i suggest and the the the
difficulty
the reason we don't already have these
as political topics
is that they are inherently difficult uh
they're
inherently difficult they're inherently
multi-dimensional inherently relational
contextual hard to see hard to grasp
even for the individual like sometimes
you know you find yourself in life and
you ask yourself am i happy this is this
is this working out and during the same
day
you can have wildly different
interpretations well there's that
nagging doubt
and actually i've always known that and
then you can see
a bit later no actually these things
work out in this way and
it's all been part of a bigger narrative
where
i'm going to in this direction and i'm
learning and i'm growing and i'm happy
i mean the more subtle stuff we we pick
up on
the more difficult it is to make a
shared
commitment to describing it to uh
do something about it and but
it's still the most that subtle stuff
that goes on
on the inside of it each of us is still
what makes life worth
living and still what life is ultimately
about it's not about a dollar baseline
or or an unemployment rate or something
else it's about
what it is to be alive and what it feels
like and what
where we find meaning if we have love if
we're
happy if we sleep well if there is
beauty in our lives
all that stuff so how can we somehow
rein those things into collective
consciousness and then make sure
that i mean we can't control them hey
life happens like you said and we you
can't you can't
you can't order somebody to be happy or
give them a friend
by the way by means of the welfare state
or where whatever
but you can create generative conditions
you can create good soil and bad soil
you can sow good seeds and bad seeds
right
and there are likelihoods here which
are empirically knowable and the
likelihoods might
be complex so you do let's say let's say
we do
intervention a and it creates these 20
great consequences
only they're just visible after 10 years
plus they create
three really bad consequences which are
visible already after three years
for instance i mean there are many such
difficult things to measure or see
but the fact that they're difficult to
measure or see
that they're more in a sense qualitative
i'm doing quotation marks here
on qualitative that they're more
qualitative doesn't make them
any less real or any less important
rather of course
and everybody knows this i suppose those
subtle things
are the most important things and
somehow then we
are basing our whole economic and
political systems
on things that are i mean quite
obviously not the most important
things in life so it doesn't make sense
very good extension and you know you and
i have talked about the facts i'm a
pretty hardcore scientific realist
but i've also studied enough cognitive
science and cognitive neuroscience
to know that the subjective is not only
real
but it's more real than anything else to
us ourself
right and so it is odd that you know we
have somehow
in at least modern society drawn a band
around the subjective state and said
it's not the government's business
basically particularly in the
anglo-saxon sphere i mean
again when i talk about these ideas to
you know
working-class rural americans they say
what kind of economy is that
right but in reality it's the most real
thing to us
are we happy in and of ourself are we
suffering
do we feel rich in our relationships etc
and you know i agree with you that it
seems a natural
next step for what a social operating
system is
getting a little short on time here
let's move along a little bit to sort of
how we do this
and some of the important ideas one of
the
important ideas which i resonated with
strongly is your concept of attractor
points
and that winning the game is getting the
attractor points
right could you talk about that a little
yes so
um the attractor points well it's from
complex systems right
if you study the many different states a
system can
can enter into and you know this better
than i there
tend to be certain very likely outcomes
that
after you've done many enough iterations
and
it tends to stabilize around a certain
around a certain point and and that
certain point tends to
be describable and have certain space or
certain properties in this in the larger
system
so an example would be
for societal systems there appear to be
such things as
chiefdoms this is described very well in
robert wright's writing or in
francis fukuyama's writings or element
service that um
anthropologists and they describe
that once societies have a certain level
of abundance doesn't
necessarily have to have agriculture it
can be horticultural and and
just a rich hunter-gatherer society such
as the northwest
of of uh pre-columbian america
they tend to stabilize
around something called chiefdom's
chiefdoms namely that
many villages will have one and the same
chief
and that chief will be very very adored
and they will also exploit people and
they will be very looked up to
some kind of authoritarian relationship
shows up
and the german you can see this around
the globe then you can see it in latin
america you can see it in papua new
guinea you can see it across the pacific
ocean and and
polynesia you can see it in the germanic
tribes encountered by
julius caesar when he went there you can
see it in the middle east you can see it
in um archaeological evidence from china
before
before its kingdoms and so on so if
this same structure or a corresponding
structure shows up in so many places
in so many different times but under
corresponding circumstances yes this is
an attractor point
and in that sense it does that doesn't
say
that teleologically reality or god wants
us to
evolve in this direction or something
like that it just says that
hey given these these settings and given
enough time
and given this dynamics ongoing this is
highly likely to occur but it might also
not occur something
something else can happen uh you can get
hit by a comet or whatever and then it
doesn't happen
i hold them that attractor points
are real also in our time and in our
society
another simple example somebody invented
electricity and light bulbs a while ago
and today the whole world
over the whole human world with some few
small exceptions
is electrified and it has electric light
and why is that well because it was an
attractor point that once this existed
it wouldn't roll back it wouldn't cease
to to exist or appear and likewise the
internet is a strong attractive point
and then the proliferation and
importance of the internet and
today the average person spends
a good spite of seven hours in
online interactions of different kinds
and
that's an incredibly strong attractive
point
so knowing such points
in directionalities well that doesn't
let us predict the future i mean it
doesn't make us into mediums
but it helps it helps to see
to at least rule out some
ways of thinking and acting in the world
and it makes us
more open to other ways of thinking and
acting in the world
so my my suggestion is that people
should try to train our ability of
a basic futurism or basic futurology
and try to see highly likely attractor
points
and not visual thinking or utopias or
scenarios
that we wish or or dystopian scenarios
but just things that are likely to
happen
and if you see those attractor points
relatively well and see how they are
qualitatively different
from the society of today then
when you maneuver through life through
business through the arts
through academia and research through
administration organization
uh and politics of course then on
average and over time
you will end up in a better place in the
labyrinth because you'll have hints
of where to go take a left or right to
go left or right
go straight forward and
if you have those hints those north
stars then
more people on average will walk
in unison or in parallel or in
alignment towards some kind of shared
common goal
and that's shared my mind would be
what i call a more meta-modern society
than
yeah can you get explicit about maybe
what some of these attractor points
might be or what a system of attractor
points
what comes next you know in our game b
world we often talk about basins of
attraction which are
multiple dimensions of attractors
operating to produce a coherent
container which is a dynamic social
operating system
you know maybe some ideas you have about
what metamodernism
and its attractor points look like for
me this is a
somewhat of a prequel to to the main
argument so i haven't
i'm not really a petrologist myself
just naming a few that that i do
feel are are they have to do
a lot with technology with the
environment and with uh political
social structures and cultural
expressions
one being as we have mentioned
proliferation of
intelligent machines and designed
biology
because the drives to achieve these
things and the
rewards are so vast even
if our more utopian friends or the
techno optimists or or
even according to the more pessimistic
and realistic
forecasts somehow this is going to
absolutely change
the labor market all of our
relationships the nature of work
the nature of what it means to be human
the systems
the distribution of goods and services
the the skills needed the scaffolding
for each person
all of these things are going to change
according to some kind of uh matrix of
automation
so that's one attractor point another
attractive point is
there is going to be more and more data
um gathered about each of us and our
consumer behavior
and all other forms of behavior and they
there will be
stronger and stronger predictive
algorithms which
there will be power struggles to control
another one is the environment will go
more and more to bits and and
causes more and more trouble and
another one is in developed democracies
after some ifs and bots with populist
uprisings and reactions people will want
co-developmental politics meaning
politics of
a deeper democracy because the
the fundamental party political system
and representative democracy system
was based on the classes uh
representation of the class interests of
industrial society
those classes do no longer exist in that
same form or sense
and for this reason people are going to
create different
political uh ideas and ideals and and
collaborations another one is
as globalization occurs even with a
considerable dent
due to corona crisis due to the trade
wars and donald trump and all the rest
of it
as as globalization nevertheless
uh does occur even then
the pyramids of wealth distribution of
societies around the world
will break down and they will form one
big pyramid
sometimes the left and the right talk
past each other here that
the rights say well we live in a fear
and and a freer world right and the
libertarian right and the the left
they say no inequality has been growing
in the usa
and even in sweden and so on and of
course what's happening is that
what used to be relatively equal small
pyramids
but were placed high up in the in the
global ranking
once you put everyone in the same
economic system
with no sealed containers then everybody
forms one big pyramid instead
or or one big christmas tree to be exact
it's a good way to think about it i'd
like to make one other point about
attractors which is
in complex systems we talk about
bifurcation points in a complex system
space
where there may be multiple attractors
that one could fall into
but you don't necessarily fall into them
all and i think one of the biggest
things about those of us thinking about
steering the world towards a better form
of what comes next
there are also some bad attractor points
out there if we look
at history feudalism which i am now
calling neo-feudalism as the extreme
form of libertarianism
is certainly an attractor a neo-dark
ages where religious fundamentalists
somehow defeat
us all and we fall back into a thousand
years worth of superstition
perhaps the most dangerous is
neo-fascism and the chinese model kind
of
nationalism plus militarism plus
high-tech dictatorship
i could see the world falling into that
so when we think about attractor points
and we can think about these good
attractors or the
attractors that we think lead to more
beneficial what comes next
i think it's real important to realize
that we're essentially fighting a
strategic battle against
the marble falling into one of these bad
basins of attraction
yes um i i mean i couldn't agree more
jim and uh
and you mentioned actually my favorite
bad attractor
i mean of course there there are there
there are
i suppose there there's one good
attractor point and there are two
bad attractor points if you look at
these collective basins
so one really bad attractor point uh or
attractive basin would be
some kind of fragmentation of the world
system basically
it falls apart we fail to uphold
the flows of good services and energy
and information
and then we start dying and we start
killing each other would be really bad
and i suppose that's the most sinister
one but almost as sinister in some ways
more nightmarish is global dictatorship
attractor point uh which um
this this is an argument made by yuval
harari very very
well made that capitalism could
out-compete communism
because it had decentralized
decision-making
inadvertently it also meant that
democracy would
uh in in this sense that
that we know it today the conventional
liberal democracy
could out-compete authoritarianism in
that same age
uh because uh it just
decentralized all of those decisions and
all the
economic organization into all of those
different businesses which then competed
and then
each of them had the incentives to make
the best decisions as if their
businesses depended on
upon it as if their lives depended upon
it and then in the end they
they processed more information more
sensitively and more productively
and they evolved better um
so that so that the whole system as a
whole was much more
resilient and much more open to change
and
much more highly developmental and so on
so people coordinated their agency
better
what harare mentioned is that well what
if
we're reaching the point today where you
can actually gather enough data
about people to control their agency
and have enough algorithms that are
advanced enough
that you can actually do that better
from a centralized position
thinking more in the direction of china
but also
some of the stuff that's been going on
in israel about surveillance and so on
we may very well be entering an
informational
environment or technological stage in
which
autocracy an advanced form of digital
autocracy
is actually more powerful not
necessarily at creating happy dignified
human lives but just as
at the coordinating human agency and
controlling human beings
then is a decentralized system and
then incidentally that would knock out
any democratic and a free
liberal order um and
china i i concur that's the
that's the main threat to the world
liberal order not not saying anything
bad about the chinese culture
or talking down the the great
achievements of china's economy and
civilization over the last decades
but as a political order at this point
we're at a point in history where
they are more and more challenging the
world system of liberal information
flows meaning they
have started to bully countries and
buy off governments and in
the u.n for instance and capture
journalists even outside of their own
borders
if they are criticized which is unique
uh in in in our time that this happens
yeah we have to fight this one there's
no doubt about it
yeah yeah so so the third the third the
good basin would be well taking the good
from
both of these bad examples so that we
have
fragmentation but the good thing about
fragmentation is
at least you're free you're free to be
miserable but
at least you're free um and
the bad basin uh
the authoritarian one is that you're not
free and you're miserable
but at least you're ordered when you're
in an ordered
and safe setting you can imagine then
that the
modern world order would be one of
deeper democracy which still manages to
coordinate us on a global level so it
would be ordered and free
i suppose that's
a good way to think about it let's talk
briefly about another i thought
very important concept which again i've
started to use and encourage other
people to use
which is as we think about tactics how
we actually go from where we are to
where we want to be
you talk about the ideas of game
acceptance game denial
and game change a little bit of detail
on each of those would be great
yes sure so roughly speaking
most people are stuck in either game
denial or game acceptance
and game denial is all the idealistic
people and
it's uh most of all the sin of uh of the
of the left i suppose and game denial
is basically that you want to somehow
there's a utopian impulse that you want
to remove
unfairness and reality and then
you're trying to move towards a place
where competition would be abolished
where people would just be kind and
actually i see
some of this even in in game b
formulations i i get a bit of game
denial vibes when
they say we want to move into a
non-rivalrous game or
a non-competitive game and that we're
currently in a rivalrous game or
rivalrous civilization
and that includes a number of logical
impossibilities i mean things can't be
several things at once maybe at a
quantum level but for instance
any time there is a relationship
there is also a power relationship and
that power relationship
is always dependent on some kind of
properties or strengths of the involved
even
even down to you know parent child stuff
or
or lovers or partners or
certainly humans and animals it just
goes
it just goes through all of it so so
it's difficult to
to reach that point that ultimate point
of
no competition and for this reason
that's not necessarily the best goal and
what happens is in great
practice this has very practical
implications if you look at the
left parties around europe you don't
have these in the
in the us but you have i don't know
campus
radicalism and and left idealism of
different kinds
if you look at these policies that they
see
in all seriousness suggest and that they
would implement if they were
to given the reins of power of
government in european countries they
would open the borders
they would lower uh order and
and crime delinquency
uh justice system stuff
and they would raise the subsidies to
normal people and and they would secure
your jobs more and make it harder to
kick people from from their work or
to sac people and they would increase
the environmental regulations and other
regulations of
companies and what would happen in
reality is not that
left utopia would emerge rather the
countries would be
swamped with immigration they would eat
and
immigrants would be paid a lot of
subsidy money at the same time this
would cause great costs
to the tax system and businesses and
businesses would
dwindle and they would be out competed
by foreign capital
and people would actually be stuck in
in their jobs and not be sacked so that
the low movement of the labor
would mean that you had a very high
unemployment at the very same time
so that the whole system would collapse
in a matter of 10 years
that's what would actually happen if you
did all of these idealist things
and that's in game denial you're denying
that there
there are games that there are choices
that have to be made
preferences and so on that there are
priorities that have to be made
moving from there to game acceptance
that's
just the opposite so a fascist will or
or a conservative
they will tend to think well life is
tough
if it wasn't fair to you tough your
problem
you work it out and then in the long run
it's going to be fair either way if
everybody just plays the game and some
people are going to be rich
others are going to be poor and what
they end up doing
is conversely defending all sorts of
injustices
that actually are quite malleable
and quite changeable and didn't
necessarily have to
be that way and you can go back through
history
so conservatives were against universal
suffrage they were against the ovulation
of slavery they were against
well pretty much anything reasonable and
good that you can think of
that was brought on by radical politics
in all of these steps they would always
argue that it's
it wouldn't be possible it doesn't have
to change it's actually fair
they were arguing according to game
acceptance
and that's what you have today as well
so game change
again is is the basser child of these
two things she kind of like
met a modern good bass and would be the
bastard child of
fragmentation and and authoritarianism
or digital authoritarianism then you
take the positive sides of both those
things and you get
where you want to go so the positive
side of of game
denial is that you refuse to accept
injustices that are arbitrary and that
can be changed
you say that okay the game that exists
today
is not good enough it's not treating
people well it's not treating animals
well it's not
justifiable and if you look at the game
acceptance part
you say but the game is there there is a
game there always has been there always
will be
so what's the conclusion you work
to learn the game play it lovingly
understand its rules and work to change
it you can
change the rules of the game and this
has happened throughout history so it
can happen again
the the lives that we live in
modern let's say sweden and
the us is considerably different from
i don't know what it might have been in
mamluk egypt
in the 12th century it would have been
quite different and the games of life
uh the stakes we played for it if we
insulted the king back then
or the sultan we would um literally
be tortured and killed so we we played
on a different game board and a society
was ruled by a slave army
so you could actually only advance by
joint by being kidnapped as a young kid
and then advance by by battling where we
whereas we can advance
by uh i don't know uh inventing
something nice and starting a nighty
business
for instance so the games are quite
different
but they're still games and they're
still winners and losers and there
always will be
that's wonderful i found that an
extraordinarily useful perspective and i
would encourage other people to
when they read the book to get their
head around those three things and
try to keep your head in the game change
space and not fall into either of those
other two
basins now we're going to turn to the
heart of the matter at least in my mind
the heart of the matter with respect to
how do we actually do this stuff
and that is what you called your master
pattern six parts
of different kinds of politics that
interoperate together
and that you argue can if executed well
move us towards a
relative utopia so i'd like you to start
first briefly defining what you meant by
relative utopia and then take us through
the six parts
and to the degree we have time how they
inter-operate
to move us towards a relative utopia
right so thank you for asking and i mean
i just
recently came across this other term
protopia
um something somebody also suggested the
the word
utopia with the eu the good place rather
than
utopias and the nowhere place but of
course it's a play on words
back in thomas morris uh
initial initial formulation in the in
the 16th century
he wrote about utopia which was a play
on words with about
it's the place that doesn't exist and
the good place
protopia then is another term for
it's not then a utopian static vision
about
what society can and should be like and
then everybody will be happy
rather it's a relative place which is
obviously preferable for most people
than the current state of affairs so
protopia is
just somewhere you want to move but
which is still
qualitatively different from where we're
at today
and that's also what i mean with with
the relative utopia
uh vision there are there are a bunch of
different authors today uh
who have brought up visions of relative
utopia there's this
dutch historian um who wrote it's called
utopia for realist right his book and
it's about
basic income and open borders i don't
believe
actually his his program uh or
or the argument made in his book but
he's playing around
with the very fact that from the
perspective
of 200 years ago what we're experiencing
today
is a utopia in many ways
of course not everybody's happy and
there are all sorts of horrible things
but just if you if you take the the
average
experience of everyday life and ex
of a middle-class person today versus a
farmer in the
in the early 1800s then the difference
is just
unimaginable and it does and if we we
describe what we had for dinner
and which parts of the world we've been
to
and what kind of privileges we have and
so on it would sound utopian
and in that sense we're in a relative
utopia when a
utopia that would seem utopian
to the farmer of 200 years ago now
if that has happened again and again
throughout history that
we have created relative utopias and
particularly now and
with the advent of modernity would it be
so strange
if in 200 years society will look like a
relative utopia
to us and that it would be qualitatively
different
in ways that we almost can't imagine
that's that's the argument that if that
if that's how
that is what has consistently happened
many times through history
already wouldn't we be fooling ourselves
for saying okay we're not going to talk
about
utopian visions because they only lead
us to gulag
when we know that is what has happened
relative utopia at least so how do we do
it let's talk about the master pattern
and the
six kinds of politics that we need to
master
oh yeah so so that's the biggest part of
the book and then the
the biggest part of the argument i
suppose um the
the first part is to see that
politics and what we mean
by the word politics changes over time
so
all of the basics were there already in
sumerian civilization for instance that
well you would have um you would have a
minister of war you would have a
minister of
taxes you would have a minister of
education and
and then of course somebody would be
something like a prime minister
and then of course in in the sumerian
society you had a
you had a king or a god king something
like that
throughout the development of more and
more complex societies
more roles have been taken up by society
so i mean in babylon you had the
organization of
municipal brothels for instance
and whereas in rome you had
well you had all of the the building of
aqueducts and and all sorts of of public
things that had to do with the
with the colosseums and the
amphitheaters and
many different things that that evolve
over time
which the public realm take up something
and and begin to develop techniques and
experiences shared experiences
for dealing with something that formally
wasn't
viewed as part of politics
[Music]
and this is difficult and it's
controversial because it's i mean
how far should politics expand it's not
it's and
and how far can can it realistically
expand what we see though is that there
is a direction of
a developmental direction here and it's
not necessarily in the direction of
more control of every each and every
individual
but it is in the direction of
somehow organizing and coordinating on
more and more
domains of life the last
large example of such a major shift is
probably environmental politics so
back in the 1800s u.s government
created something like uh the ministry
of forestry and
and and not it wasn't called the
environmental ministry at that point
but from now a hundred years after that
almost all countries had some kind of
environmental
ministry or department dealing
with environmental issues now
what we have seen a tendency towards and
it's very tentative and it's very
it just flickers past here and there
there is a minister of loneliness in the
uk
there was a minister of the future in um
in sweden there was a minister of
happiness in some country i keep
forgetting which one
bhutan well perhaps in bhutan i'm not
sure
uh so in bhutan of course there's the
gdp
there's the gross national happiness
thing and and all of that stuff
uh maybe there is also minister of
happiness there but they're a minister
of yoga in in
current uh current india perhaps not the
most progressive food
in the world but if you take these
different
um they point
uh these two different tendencies they
point towards
somehow that politics wants to deal
with issues of mental health of personal
development
of human relationships of inner
dimensions
which we talked about earlier in this
interview right
and as we also mentioned these things
are difficult
to grasp these things are difficult to
corner
and clearly get our hands on as objects
and for this reason we may need several
forms of new politics which balance each
other out
and take different dimensions of what it
means to organize as human beings in
societies
and what it means to be a human being in
the first place
and let these evolve together
so that they
they can they can triangulate or
with more angles and three really uh
these
more complex and subtle issues of life
and
somehow make put them at the heart and
center of how we organize
our societies so to
to mention uh some of these forms of
politics which
i suggest one would be existential
politics
meaning politics of
looking into how meaningful people find
their lives and
how purpose-driven people's lives are
and how free we really feel
on the inside whether or not we have
struggle with
issues of death and anxiety and so on
and see if well what can
possibly be done here in terms of
education in terms of health care
in terms of preventive measures it's an
important issue like how are people
feeling
really feeling deep down like
are we living our lives to the fullest
or to
to the the best possible extent that we
can
and somehow that issue never shows up in
politics because it's
thought of as part of the personal realm
and the private realm
but quite obviously it depends upon
other people and depends upon the social
structures that we're part of
so it should be perhaps made
into a conscious and explicit form of
politics
which would include its own censuses and
so
methods of scientific surveying and so
on
but that's just that's just one one side
of this
another side would be the relationships
to one another
and ethnic relationships familial
relationships
uh commun local community relationships
uh engagement in civic life
identification with different groups
uh relationships between different
religions and society
relationships between the genders all of
these things have to do with
humans relating to one another which in
turn have to do with social skills
perspective taking the amount of
tolerance and empathy that people feel
or have the capacity to feel
what really takes people off about
different things
and well these issues can quite
obviously also be developed and today
we're seeing all sorts of fallout of
relationships that don't work throughout
society
but we have no real way of attending to
those
those issues so the second one is what i
call
get mineshaft politics and the mineshaft
is a bit of a
tricky word and so i i
picked the german word because there
wasn't an exact corresponding one in
in english gemini means something like
community
or relationship or fellowship in in the
abstract sense
are togetherness i suppose you could say
and somehow togetherness can be
have higher or lower quality and it can
be
more pervasive or less pervasive it can
wrought with with issues and conflicts
and problems or it can be
more pure and and and
resonate in a more harmonic manner
so this is a very very very important
source of happiness and misery in pretty
much everybody's life
and right now we're more or less leaving
it outside
of uh the budgeting of
our self-organization as as political
units so we're just leaving it up to
chance really this most important part
of what it means to be human and again
it's not about
then creating a welfare state where you
can go to the to the welfare office and
get a friend
and that's not what we're talking about
we're talking about generative
conditions or
whatever can nimbly and intelligently
be made in terms of interventions or
preventive measures
or equipping people with the right
skills and
and the context and so on to get these
things to work as well as possible
and then of course refine what we mean
by good relationships throughout society
so those are two dimensions um we're not
going to go through i suppose all six in
in the same detail but just to mention
then
a couple of things about the other ones
the other ones
are try to balance these
out because both of these things
existence
and what if what really feels like to be
alive
and and relationships they're they're
very personal matters right
and the very personal matters here uh
they
they need to be balanced when when they
become political they need to somehow be
balanced out
by issues that are um
that by politics that protect
us from more subtle forms
of transgression in these areas so
that's why we might need something like
emancipation politics
like a politics which a kind of politics
with its
own uh ministry and its own
department which pushes and perhaps its
own parties
which pushes against these these more
integrative processes
these processes that have to do with uh
with meddling with people's lives with
the improving upon
relationships and going deeper into the
personal emancipation politics
politics of freedom of conflicts of
protecting
the individual's rights would push
against
these other two from there on we might
imagine a fourth
kind of politics empirical politics
meaning that each of these things need
to be formulated in ways that
actually make sense and actually have
intended effects
so society needs to become a lot more
scientific than it currently is
most of policy decision making today is
based
quite loosely on science and science can
be
expanded and we can have much stronger
knowledge about
why we're doing things and how we're
doing things
so that would be a fourth dimension an
empirical dimension
which then is in a way third person
reality or
objective reality pushing back against
these
things that come from the subjective
realm so we get to know
the inter-subjective realm or the
objective realm and try to
validate these more subtle forms of
politics
then this would bring us to a fifth one
all of this
requires a deeper legitimacy which
requires a deepening of democracy so
the kind of democracy that we have today
is relatively representative and distant
and bureaucratic if we are to enter into
these
more intimate realms of human
development
we must also in different ways deepen
the legitimacy and participation
and humanization of the democratic
system and that is an
ongoing process which may require its
own
political impetus and perhaps its own
political proponents and so on
and that should be an ongoing process
maybe that society should
invest a lot in this issue
improving upon its own
modes of governance maybe a couple of
percent of the gdp
would go to perpetually try to improve
and challenge
how science governs itself making it
more transparent more participatory more
intelligent
in its decision making and making its
decisions
more legitimate to the citizens more
felt
as their own which brings us to the last
form of politics
and that's where we started in this
interview i suppose and
a good place to uh to draw towards an
end
is that the the last form of politics
the sixth form
would be politics of theory meaning a
politics
of how we describe reality and how we
brainwash ourselves as society we said
that
i said early on that a meta-modern
society is different
from a modern society in that modern
society changes nature
according to its cultural uh to its
cultural code
but a meta-modern society must be able
to see its own cultural code
and change also what it means to be
human and how the interpretations
that are in in its culture uh affect
our our everyday life and agency and
that everyday life itself
can be different including how we view
reality
and our place in it so this in itself
should become a political issue of
course balanced by all of the others
you need a strong empirical pushback
here you need
democratic participation in these kinds
of processes
but the the fundamental issue about what
stories about reality do people have and
how can those
be improved upon and bridged in the best
possible way
is a question that has immense
importance even to our very survival as
that's the species and society and so on
so
uh so we can't really avoid the issue
what what reality what sense of reality
do we have and that should be placed at
the very heart of politics
this shouldn't be the first step in
introducing a meta-modern politics
but these six forms of politics together
they form
a kind of master pattern that if you try
to do one of them they won't really work
if you try to do two of them they might
balance out a little bit
but if you do all six there is a logic
to it
that makes it makes them hopefully or as
far as i can see
balance out more and they should also be
viewed as some being more difficult
than others so the politics of theory is
that in a sense the heaviest one but
also the most difficult one that relies
most upon
the former ones well very good
i should really thank you for a very
nice in-depth explication of the ideas
in this book
and i'll tell the listeners we got to
about half of my topics and questions
once again the book
nordic ideology is incredible in its
richness
and those of you out there in listener
land who are interested in thinking
deeply seriously and originally about
what comes next i
strongly endorse you read nordic
ideology
so hanzi i want to thank you again for
coming on the show and i'm going to
invite you back for a third time talk
about some of the things we didn't talk
about
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com